Podcast Episode #9
Mephibosheth
You are listening to Lutheran.radio in Finnish.
Unbroken Promises — The story of David and Mephibosheth
In the first book of Samuel, David and Jonathan form a covenant of friendship.
Two chapters earlier, the prophet Samuel has anointed David as king.
The first four verses of that chapter 18 read as follows:
And it came to pass, when he had made an end of speaking unto Saul,
that the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David,
and Jonathan loved him as his own soul.
And Saul took him that day,
and would let him go no more home to his father's house.
Then Jonathan and David made a covenant,
because he loved him as his own soul.
And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him, and gave it to David,
and his garments, even to his sword, and to his bow, and to his girdle.
When a Christian prays the Lord's Prayer
give us … our daily bread,
that daily bread also includes good friends.
David was very blessed to have such a friend as Jonathan.
In the same 1 Sam. 20 chapter,
Jonathan asks, adjures
David to show mercy to his own family
after Jonathan's death.
In verse 15 Jonathan says:
“But also thou shalt not cut off thy kindness from my house for ever”
And David kept that promise.
And to understand it more easily,
one must still look at 2 Sam. 4:4,
when Saul and his sons are already dead.
There's the tragedy of Mephibosheth
where Mephibosheth becomes disabled in an accident.
That verse reads as follows:
And Jonathan, Saul's son, had a son that was lame of his feet.
He was five years old when the tidings came of Saul and Jonathan out of Jezreel,
and his nurse took him up, and fled:
and it came to pass, as she made haste to flee,
that he fell, and became lame.
And his name was Mephibosheth.
David wanted to remember Jonathan's request:
“But also thou shalt not cut off thy kindness from my house for ever”
So David in 2 Sam. 9 asks:
Is there yet any that is left of the house of Saul, that I may shew him kindness for Jonathan's sake?
And there was of the house of Saul a servant whose name was Ziba. And when they had called him unto David,
the king said unto him, Art thou Ziba?
And he said, Thy servant is he.
And the king said, Is there not yet any of the house of Saul, that I may shew the kindness of God unto him?
And Ziba said unto the king, Jonathan hath yet a son, which is lame on his feet.
And the king said unto him, Where is he?
And Ziba said unto the king, Behold, he is in the house of Machir, the son of Ammiel, in Lodebar.
Then king David sent, and fetched him out of the house of Machir, the son of Ammiel, from Lodebar.
Now when Mephibosheth, the son of Jonathan, the son of Saul, was come unto David, he fell on his face, and did reverence.
And David said, Mephibosheth. And he answered, Behold thy servant!
And David said unto him, Fear not: for I will surely shew thee kindness for Jonathan thy father's sake,
and will restore thee all the land of Saul thy father; and thou shalt eat bread at my table continually.
So David sought out Mephibosheth and restored his family's land to him.
Then after this, Mephibosheth is invited to eat at David's table,
in verse 11 and onwards:
Then said Ziba unto the king, According to all that my lord the king hath commanded his servant, so shall thy servant do.
As for Mephibosheth, said the king, he shall eat at my table, as one of the king's sons.
And Mephibosheth had a young son, whose name was Micha. And all that dwelt in the house of Ziba were servants unto Mephibosheth.
So Mephibosheth dwelt in Jerusalem: for he did eat continually at the king's table;
and was lame on both his feet.
King David was not bothered by the fact that Mephibosheth was lame.
The kings of that time would rather have hidden a lame person out of sight from the court.
But David did not want to do so, as he had promised otherwise.
But then a little later something happens that interrupts that invitation to eat at the king's sons' table.
Therefore, when King David's son Absalom rebels
and David has to flee to save his life,
the expectation was that all of David's friends would have come with him.
But for some reason, Mephibosheth did not show up.
In 2 Sam. 16 chapter,
that same Ziba, who told David about Mephibosheth, now tells him something completely different about him.
Chapter 16 reads as follows:
And when David was a little past the top of the hill, behold, Ziba the servant of Mephibosheth met him,
with a couple of asses saddled,
and upon them two hundred loaves of bread,
and an hundred bunches of raisins,
and an hundred of summer fruits, and a bottle of wine.
And the king said unto Ziba, What meanest thou by these?
And Ziba said, The asses be for the king's household to ride on; and the bread and summer fruit for the young men to eat; and the wine, that such as be faint in the wilderness may drink.
And the king said, And where is thy master's son?
And Ziba said unto the king, Behold, he abideth at Jerusalem: for he said, To day shall the house of Israel restore me the kingdom of my father.
Then said the king to Ziba, Behold, thine are all that pertained unto Mephibosheth.
And Ziba said, I humbly beseech thee that I may find grace in thy sight, my lord, O king.
The Bible accurately repeats what Ziba said,
but does not actually tell whether the matter was as Ziba said.
The previous text could just as well be titled: “Ziba's Deception”
After all, with that, Ziba now got the land property for himself, which King David had returned to Mephibosheth.
Then a little later, in 2 Sam. 19 chapter
Mephibosheth explains his own version of the story upon David's return.
It reads as follows:
And Mephibosheth the son of Saul came down to meet the king,
and had neither dressed his feet, nor trimmed his beard, nor washed his clothes, from the day the king departed until the day he came again in peace.
Kun hän nyt tuli Jerusalemista kuningasta vastaan, sanoi kuningas hänelle:
Wherefore wentest not thou with me, Mephibosheth?
And he answered, My lord, O king, my servant deceived me:
for thy servant said,
I will saddle me an ass, that I may ride thereon, and go to the king;
because thy servant is lame.
And he hath slandered thy servant unto my lord the king;
but my lord the king is as an angel of God: do therefore what is good in thine eyes.
For all of my father's house were but dead men before my lord the king:
yet didst thou set thy servant among them that did eat at thine own table.
What right therefore have I yet to cry any more unto the king?
And the king said unto him, Why speakest thou any more of thy matters?
I have said, Thou and Ziba divide the land.
And Mephibosheth said unto the king, Yea, let him take all, forasmuch as my lord the king is come again in peace unto his own house.
So the most important thing for Mephibosheth was that David forgave him anyway, regardless of what David thought,
whether he believed Ziba's explanation or Mephibosheth's,
regardless of that, David forgave Mephibosheth
and restored his place back at his table.
In Acts 13:22-23,
King David is being described with these words:
And when he had removed him [Saul],
he raised up unto them David to be their king;
to whom also he gave testimony, and said,
I have found David the son of Jesse, a man after mine own heart, which shall fulfil all my will.
Of this man's seed hath God according to his promise raised unto Israel a Saviour, Jesus
and indeed,
David reminded very much of Christ, especially in 2 Sam. 9.
In verse one, David asked:
Is there yet any that is left of the house of Saul, that I may shew him kindness for Jonathan's sake?
Christ has done the greatest possible mercy to mankind by reconciling people with God on the cross.
And Christ wants to show mercy because of that new covenant.
And just as David restored Mephibosheth's inheritance,
so Christ also restores all that spiritual inheritance that can only be obtained in Him.
Then perhaps the finest is this in verse ten:
“but Mephibosheth thy master's son shall eat bread always at my table.”
Precisely the same way, Christ invites all His believers to His own table already in this life.
Just as David gave Mephibosheth a place to dine in the company of the king's sons,
in the same way, Christ gives you a place at the table of the Lord's Supper.
The invitation to the king's table is valid because of Christ.
And then there's that last one too,
despite the accusations against Mephibosheth, David forgives.
Just as Christ also forgives our sins.
https://www.lutheran.radio